so the argument for raid 6 being an
overkill is that
when in raid 5 a disk fails it takes up
to a couple of days to replace sometimes
you have a spare disk and usually a data
center will have that so it's going to
take less than an hour
and there is a very very low probability
that another disk in the array will fail
in those three days
if it fails after these three days it
doesn't matter because by then we are
back to being protected by the extra
disk so the failure of the second disk
needs to happen in the time
when one of the disk is in the failed
state
but that assumes that the disk failures
are independent
but the failures can be related to each
other in which case this is not correct
to assume
a typical scenario when this can happen
is let's say that we have a raid five
with five disks and one of the disk
fails let's say that disk number two in
the array has failed
the system reports that the disk has
failed and continues functioning
normally remember that it can do that
with one failed disk in raid 5. and now
the operator gets a replacement disk
opens the computer case and sees five
drives like this
knows that the number two has failed so
it takes this one out and puts the new
drive in
but for example the numbering of the
disks was actually zero one two three
four so we pulled out the wrong drive
this was the failed one
when we pulled this second one
that was the second failure and now we
really have two failed disks one
failed because it failed the other one
failed in the course of trying to repair
the first failure so that's for example
a case of correlated failures and
in that case we cannot assume
independence so pretty much when a disk
fails
the actions to repair it
are creating a lot more risk for the
other disks
and may cause a second failure
and that for example where you want to
have raid six when one fails and you're
trying to repair it
if another one fails for any reason
independent or dependent on the first
failure you are still safe